Donald Winnicott Papers Finding Aid
Oskar Diethelm Library
Donald Winnicott Papers
1930 - 1987
This collection contains the papers of Donald Winnicott, who was known for his studies on the mother-infant relationship, the process of separation, and the use of the transitional object (e.g. the blanket or the teddy bear). The collection has 3 series: Correspondence, Unpublished Papers, and Oral History.
4.59 linear feet (11 boxes)
Winnicott, D. W. (Donald Woods), 1896-1971
Oskar Diethelm Library DeWitt Wallace Institute of Psychiatry: History, Policy and the Arts Weill Cornell Medical College 525 East 68th Street, Box 140 New York, NY 10065
1980.0001
The correspondence, unpublished papers, and patient case records of Donald Woods Winnicott were donated by Winnicott’s widow, Clare Winnicott, in 1980 and received by the Diethelm Library in 1981 and 1984. The audiotapes were donated by Dr. Michael Neve on January 15, 1986.
The correspondence and patient case records were microfilmed prior to final processing. Therefore, the microfilm is not in exact alphabetical and chronological order within each alphabetical unit. The patient records have not been processed because of restrictions on access. The letters were originally housed in notebooks, generally one for each year, and then arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent. The original order has been retained for each year. However, within each letter of the alphabet, exact chronological and alphabetical order has been imposed. Occasionally Winnicott retained letters prior to the date on the volume if the subject matter was related. Two sets of microfilm were made; the original is stored by Microfax, the company that microfilmed the papers, and the second set has been sent to the Institute of Psycho-Analysis in London.
Some letters from patients or other physicians describe the nature of patients' illnesses. This correspondence has been segregated from the general correspondence, and access to it is restricted.
Donald Woods Winnicott (1896-1971) was born in Plymouth, Devon in England. He was educated at Leys School in Cambridge and Jesus College, Cambridge University. He began his medical career as a pediatrician at a time when there were few in Great Britain who were engaged solely in the practice of medical care of children. He was appointed Physician to the Paddington Green Children's Hospital in London in 1923. This same year, he began a personal analysis, thereby becoming more interested in child psychology. In the 1930's, he became an Associate, and then a Member, of the British Psycho-Analytical Society, which he was elected president of in 1956. His 1931 book Clinical Notes on Disorders of Childhood was one of the first books in which there was a fusing of the two aspects of pediatrics, medical care and child psychiatry. He began to specialize in antisocial behavior as a result of his work during World War II with the failure of the evacuation scheme. In Dr. Winnicott's private practice, he served as both a pediatrician and psychoanalyst for children, adolescents, and adults. Gradually, his psychoanalytic work took precedence. He taught at the London School of Economics, London University, London Institute of Education, London Institute of Psycho-Analysis, and later at the Tavistock Institute of Human Relations.
Winnicott is known for his studies on the mother-infant relationship, the process of separation, and the use of the transitional object (e.g. the blanket or the teddy bear). His writings also focus on object relations, aggression in the relationship, the true and false self, development of language, symbol formation, and creativity. Winnicott retired from Paddington Green in 1963 and continued with his private practice, lecturing, and writing before his death on January 25, 1971.
Winnicott, D. W. (Donald Woods), 1896-1971; Winnicott, Clare; Transitional objects (Psychology); Object relations (Psychoanalysis); British Psycho-Analytical Society; Tavistock Clinic; Institute of Psycho-analysis (Great Britain); Neve, Michael; Separation-individuation; Child analysis; Adolescent analysis; Psychoanalysis
This collection contains the papers of Donald Winnicott, who was known for his studies on the mother-infant relationship, the process of separation, and the use of the transitional object (e.g. the blanket or the teddy bear). There are 3 series in this collection.
Correspondence: Composed of letters with colleagues, friends, patients, the public, institutions, and organizations, which are primarily professional in nature. Correspondence concerns referrals for patients, lecture engagements, recommendations of colleagues, publication of books, and personal, familial, and business matters, and business activities of the British Psycho-Analytic Society, of which he was president of from 1956 to 1959. Occasionally the reverse sides of letters are illustrated with Winnicott’s drawings. Most of the correspondents are English, and some letters from patients or other physicians describe the nature of patients' illnesses. This correspondence has been segregated from the general correspondence, and access to it is restricted. Frequent correspondents include: Wilfred R. Bion of the London Clinic of Psycho-Analysis; Augusta Bonnard; John Bowlby of the Tavistock Clinic in London; Anna Freud; D.E.M. Gardner of the London Institute of Economics; Donald Gough of the Tavistock Clinic; David Holbrook; Susanne Isaacs (Winnicott's successor at Paddington Green, London); M. Masud R. Khan (Librarian of the Institute of Psycho-Analysis in London); London School of Economics and Political Science; Tavistock Clinic of Human Relations; and Freny Mehta of Bombay, India.
Unpublished Papers: This series primarily has typed versions of lectures and addresses to colleagues at various professional meetings and conferences or materials that appear to have been written for journals. However, some of the papers have been published since the time of Winnicott’s death, and photocopies of these papers appear in the series. Included is a list of titles of published and unpublished works that was compiled in 1975 by Dr. D.C. Wallbridge of the Winnicott Publications Committee.
Oral History: This has three audiotapes of an interview of Mrs. Clare Winnicott concerning her husband's professional work. The interview was conducted by Dr. Michael Neve in June 1983, and the tapes have been transcribed.
- Correspondence
  - A – C, 1957 (Box 1)
  - D – G, 1957 (Box 1)
  - H – K, 1957 (Box 1)
  - L – N, 1957 (Box 1)
  - O – S, 1957 (Box 1)
  - T – W, 1957 (Box 1)
  - RESTRICTED Correspondence on patients, 1957 (Box 1)
  - A – C, 1958 (Box 1)
  - D – F, 1958 (Box 1)
  - G – J, 1958 (Box 1)
  - K – L, 1958 (Box 1)
  - M – O, 1958 (Box 1)
  - P – R, 1958 (Box 1)
  - S, 1958 (Box 1)
  - T – Z, 1958 (Box 1)
  - RESTRICTED Correspondence on patients, 1958 (Box 1)
  - A – D, 1959 (Box 2)
  - E – H, 1959 (Box 2)
  - I – M, 1959 (Box 2)
  - N – R, 1959 (Box 2)
  - S – T, 1959 (Box 2)
  - W, 1959 (Box 2)
  - RESTRICTED Correspondence on patients, 1959 (Box 2)
  - A – C, 1960 (Box 2)
  - D – J, 1960 (Box 2)
  - K – L, 1960 (Box 2)
  - M – N, 1960 (Box 2)
  - R – S, 1960 (Box 2)
  - T, 1960 (Box 2)
  - V – Z, 1960 (Box 2)
  - RESTRICTED Correspondence on patients, 1960 (Box 2)
  - A – B, 1961 (Box 3)
  - C – E, 1961 (Box 3)
  - F – K, 1961 (Box 3)
  - L, 1961 (Box 3)
  - M – O, 1961 (Box 3)
  - P – S, 1961 (Box 3)
  - T – Y, 1961 (Box 3)
  - RESTRICTED Correspondence on patients, 1961 (Box 3)
  - A – D, 1962 (Box 3)
  - E – J, 1962 (Box 3)
  - K – L, 1962 (Box 3)
  - M – O, 1962 (Box 3)
  - P – R, 1962 (Box 3)
  - S – W, 1962 (Box 3)
  - RESTRICTED Correspondence on patients, 1962 (Box 3)
  - A – B, 1963 (Box 4)
  - C – G, 1963 (Box 4)
  - H – J, 1963 (Box 4)
  - K – M, 1963 (Box 4)
  - N – P, 1963 (Box 4)
  - R – Z, 1963 (Box 4)
  - RESTRICTED Correspondence on patients, 1963 (Box 4)
  - A – C, 1964 (Box 4)
  - D – G, 1964 (Box 4)
  - H – J, 1964 (Box 4)
  - K – O, 1964 (Box 4)
  - P – S, 1964 (Box 4)
  - T – Y, 1964 (Box 4)
  - RESTRICTED Correspondence on patients, 1964 (Box 4)
  - A – C, 1965 (Box 5)
  - D – F, 1965 (Box 5)
  - G – H, 1965 (Box 5)
  - I – L, 1965 (Box 5)
  - M – N, 1965 (Box 5)
  - O – S, 1965 (Box 5)
  - T – Y, 1965 (Box 5)
  - RESTRICTED Correspondence on patients, 1965 (Box 5)
  - A – B, January, 1966 - August, 1966 (Box 5)
  - C – E, January, 1966 - August, 1966 (Box 5)
  - F – H, January, 1966 - August, 1966 (Box 5)
  - I – L, January, 1966 - August, 1966 (Box 5)
  - M – P, January, 1966 - August, 1966 (Box 5)
  - R – S, January, 1966 - August, 1966 (Box 5)
  - T – W, January, 1966 - August, 1966 (Box 5)
  - RESTRICTED Correspondence on patients, January, 1966 - August, 1966 (Box 5)
  - A – B, September, 1966 - June 16, 1967 (Box 6)
  - C – E, September, 1966 - June 16, 1967 (Box 6)
  - F – G, September, 1966 - June 16, 1967 (Box 6)
  - H – K, September, 1966 - June 16, 1967 (Box 6)
  - L – M, September, 1966 - June 16, 1967 (Box 6)
  - N – R, September, 1966 - June 16, 1967 (Box 6)
  - S – Z, September, 1966 - June 16, 1967 (Box 6)
  - RESTRICTED Correspondence on patients, September, 1966 - June 16, 1967 (Box 6)
  - A – B, June 17, 1967 - March 11, 1968 (Box 6)
  - C – F, June 17, 1967 - March 11, 1968 (Box 6)
  - G – H, June 17, 1967 - March 11, 1968 (Box 6)
  - I – L, June 17, 1967 - March 11, 1968 (Box 6)
  - M – O, June 17, 1967 - March 11, 1968 (Box 6)
  - P – R, June 17, 1967 - March 11, 1968 (Box 6)
  - S, June 17, 1967 - March 11, 1968 (Box 6)
  - T – Z, June 17, 1967 - March 11, 1968 (Box 6)
  - RESTRICTED Correspondence on patients, June 17, 1967 - March 11, 1968 (Box 6)
  - A –B, March 12, 1968 - January 20, 1969 (Box 7)
  - C – G, March 12, 1968 - January 20, 1969 (Box 7)
  - H – J, March 12, 1968 - January 20, 1969 (Box 7)
  - K – L, March 12, 1968 - January 20, 1969 (Box 7)
  - M, March 12, 1968 - January 20, 1969 (Box 7)
  - O – R, March 12, 1968 - January 20, 1969 (Box 7)
  - S, March 12, 1968 - January 20, 1969 (Box 7)
  - T – Z, March 12, 1968 - January 20, 1969 (Box 7)
  - RESTRICTED Correspondence on patients, March 12, 1968 - January 20, 1969 (Box 7)
  - A – B, January 21, 1969 - August 21, 1969 (Box 7)
  - C, January 21, 1969 - August 21, 1969 (Box 7)
  - D – E, January 21, 1969 - August 21, 1969 (Box 7)
  - F – J, January 21, 1969 - August 21, 1969 (Box 7)
  - K – L, January 21, 1969 - August 21, 1969 (Box 7)
  - M, January 21, 1969 - August 21, 1969 (Box 7)
  - N – R, January 21, 1969 - August 21, 1969 (Box 7)
  - S, January 21, 1969 - August 21, 1969 (Box 7)
  - T – Z, January 21, 1969 - August 21, 1969 (Box 7)
  - A – B, August, 1969 - June, 1970 (Box 8)
  - C – F, August, 1969 - June, 1970 (Box 8)
  - G, August, 1969 - June, 1970 (Box 8)
  - H – K, August, 1969 - June, 1970 (Box 8)
  - L – O, August, 1969 - June, 1970 (Box 8)
  - P – R, August, 1969 - June, 1970 (Box 8)
  - S, August, 1969 - June, 1970 (Box 8)
  - T – Z, August, 1969 - June, 1970 (Box 8)
  - RESTRICTED Correspondence on patients, August, 1969 - June, 1970 (Box 8)
  - A – E, June, 1970 - 1971 (Box 8)
  - F – L, June, 1970 - 1971 (Box 8)
  - M – O, June, 1970 - 1971 (Box 8)
  - P – R, June, 1970 - 1971 (Box 8)
  - S – Z, June, 1970 - 1971 (Box 8)
  - RESTRICTED Correspondence on patients, 1970 (Box 8)
  - Margaret Little, Undated (Box 8)
- Unpublished Papers
  - Comprehensive index of published and unpublished work of Donald N. Winnicott, compiled by D.C. Wallbridge, August, 1975 (Box 9)
  - Outlines of planned books, Undated (Box 9)
  - Volume I, Undated (Box 9)
  - Volume I, Undated (Box 9)
  - Volume II, Undated (Box 9)
  - Volume II, Undated (Box 9)
  - Volume III, Undated (Box 10)
  - Volume III, Undated (Box 10)
  - Volume IV, Undated (Box 10)
  - Volume IV, Undated (Box 10)
- Oral History
  - “Clare Winnicott: Conversations with Dr. Michael Neve," three audiotapes (reel to reel) Dr. Michael Neve interview with Mrs. Clare Winnicott about Dr. Winnicott's work, 1983 (Box 11)
  - Cassette tape copy of interview, 1987 (Box 11)
  - Transcription of Dr. Michael Neve interview with Mrs. Clare Winnicott, Undated (Box 11)